Finding Aid for Allie Fayz papers, 1953-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allie Fayz papers
1953-2009
1989-2009
Fayz, Allie.
2010074 Aa 2
Allie Fayz is a former board member of the Islamic Center of America. The collection documents the Islamic Center of America’s history, administrative services, and community activities and consists primarily of correspondence, by-laws and amendments, board minutes, committee notes, donation pledges, membership lists, photographs, newspaper clippings, and financial statements and reports.
1.5 linear feet
1 drawers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Allie Fayz (donor no. 10330 ) in March 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Allie Fayz immigrated to the United States at the age of 16. Fayz briefly worked for the Ford Motor Company in Dearborn before taking a job in 1953 as a garage mechanic for the Truck Transport Company. In 1955, Fayz entered the United States Armed Services as a volunteer where he was stationed in Mainz, Germany. After completing his military obligation in 1957, Fayz returned to Detroit. Soon after his return, Fayz secured a job as a route salesman for the Tom's Food Company. He later advanced to district sales manager of the company. After retiring in 1988, Fayz became involved with commercial property development.
In the 1960, Allie Fayz became actively involved in the Islamic Center of America. He later served on the Board of Trustees and was valuable in the planning and construction of the Grand Mosque and new Islamic Center of America building on Ford Road in Dearborn, Michigan.
The Allie Fayz papers are organized into two series: Islamic Center of America and Other Papers. The collection consists primarily of correspondence, by-laws and amendments, board minutes, committee notes, donation pledges, membership lists, photographs, newspaper clippings, and financial statements and reports.
Subjects:
Arab Americans--Michigan.; Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Dearborn (Mich.); Fayz, Allie.; Islamic architecture--United States.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.); Muslims--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Chirri, Mohamad Jawad.; Fayz, Allie.; Guido, Michael A.; Islamic architecture--United States.; Islamic Center of America (Dearborn, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Color prints (photographs); Photographs.; Posters.; Presentation drawings (proposals)
- Islamic Center of America
  Islamic Center of America series documents the history, administrative services, and community activities of the Islamic Center. There is a significant amount of material related to the planning, construction, and completion of the Grand Mosque and new Islamic Center of America building on Ford Road in Dearborn. The series also contains papers related to the purchasing and selling of property on M-14 in Plymouth Township. Proceeds from the sale of the Plymouth Township property helped the Islamic Center purchase their current property on Ford Road. The series contains correspondence, by-laws and amendments, board minutes, committee notes, donation pledges, membership lists, photographs, newspaper clippings, and financial statements and reports.
  - Background/History, 1988-2009; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 1)
    (includes a graphical representations of the ICA stored on CD-ROM)
  - Presentation boards for ICA building (2), 1990s undated (Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees, 1996-2004; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - By-laws and amendments, 1988-1999 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2009; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Complex Construction Committee, 1994-1998 (Box 1)
  - Donation Pledges, 1998-2007; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Events, 1987-2009; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial Committee, 1995-2004 (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports and Statements, 1983-1999 (Box 1)
  - Grand Mosque
    - Background and printed material, 1998-2005; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Grand opening poster, 2005 (Folder 1)
    - "Buy a Brick to Heaven" Fundraising Campaign poster, 2005 (Folder 1)
    - Floor plans and Architectural Presentation Plans, 1998-2004 (Box 1)
    - Architectural Presentation boards (4), 1998-2004 (Folder 1)
    - Outside Reference Material, 1980s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers in Arabic, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1990-2007; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Aerial view of Islamic Center of America, 1989 (Folder 1)
    - Community and Leaders, undated (Box 1)
    - Dearborn Mayor Michael A. Guido's Trip to Lebanon, undated; 1 optical disks CD-Rs (Box 1)
      (includes a CD-ROM storing digital images)
    - Federation of Islamic Associations in U.S. & Canada Testimonial Dinner honoring Es-Sayed Kamal Rifat, 1959 (Folder 1)
    - Grand Mosque
      - Exterior and Interior, 2005 (Box 1)
      - Ground Breaking Ceremony, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Imam Chirri, 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Islamic Center of Detroit, undated (Box 1)
    - Plymouth Land Deal, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Plymouth Township Property
    - Correspondence and other papers, 1990-1999; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Closing Statements Binder, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Proposal for Islamic Center, 1989; 6 folders (Box 2)
- Other Papers
  Other Papers series contains material not related to the Islamic Center but rather documenting the life and activities of Allie Fayez. The series contains photographs, a personal interview, and speech and presentation notes.
  - Allie and Wanda Fayz 50th Anniversary Documentary Interview, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Allie Fayz and family, 1950s-1990s (Box 2)
  - Speeches and Presentations on Islam by Allie Fayz, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Biographical material (Box 2)
  - Israeli attacks on towns in southern Lebanon (Box 2)